Guide to the Agnes Boulton Collection of Eugene O'Neill
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Agnes Boulton collection of Eugene O'Neill
1910-1959
1920-1927
YCAL MSS 122
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(7 boxes)
Agnes Boulton Collection of Eugene O'Neill contains material dating from the period of Boulton's and O'Neill's marriage. Contains professional and personal correspondence (mainly incoming); writings; three diaries by Boulton and one by O'Neill; bills; legal materials regarding their houses; and photographs. Correspondents include (among others) Frederick Parsell Hill regarding Spithead (their house in Bermuda); the American Play Company, O'Neill's agent; and Harry Weinberger, O'Neill's lawyer. Writings include notes that Boulton probably made for her memoir, "Part of a Long Story" (there is also correspondence between her and Max Wylie about the book); a typescript of O'Neill's and Boulton's collaboration "The Guilty One"; typescripts of ten early poems by O'Neill; and a character study by O'Neill called "Ole Oleson's saga."
Boulton, Agnes, 1893-1968
O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Agnes Boulton and from her estate, 1963 and 1971.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 7: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
AGNES BOULTON (1893-1968)
Agnes Boulton, who was Eugene O'Neill's second wife and a writer of popular novels and short stories, was born on 19 September 1893. After Boulton and O'Neill met in New York City in the fall of 1917, they moved to Provincetown early in 1918, and were married on 12 April. They spent the fall and winter at Boulton's house in West Point Pleasant, New Jersey, and then in May 1919 moved to the former Coast Guard station (Peaked Hill Bar) in Provincetown, which was purchased for them by O'Neill's father from the writer Mabel Dodge Luhan. On 30 October 1919, their son, Shane Rudraighe, was born in Provincetown.
In the fall of 1922, the O'Neills moved to Brook Farm in Ridgefield, Connecticut, and then two years later, to Bermuda. Their daughter, Oona, was born in Bermuda on 14 May 1925. The family divided their time between Brook Farm and Bermuda (where they later bought a house, Spithead). In the summer of 1926, they rented a cottage in Belgrade Lakes, Maine, where they were visited by Boulton's daughter from her first marriage, Barbara Burton, and by O'Neill's son from his first marriage, Eugene O'Neill, Jr. It was in Belgrade Lakes that O'Neill renewed his acquaintance with Carlotta Monterey, who had starred in the 1922 New York production of his play The Hairy Ape. From that point on, O'Neill divided his time between New York and Bermuda, and between Carlotta and Boulton. In 1928, O'Neill made his choice and left on 10 February with Carlotta for Europe. Boulton tried to save the marriage, but she and O'Neill finally divorced in July 1929.
Boulton later remarried, but she and her third husband were subsequently separated. Boulton died on 25 November 1968 in West Point Pleasant, New Jersey. For further information, see Agnes Boulton's memoir, Part of a Long Story (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1958). For further information about Eugene O'Neill, see the biographical timeline in the Eugene O'Neill Papers (YCAL MSS 123).
Scope and Contents
The Agnes Boulton Collection of Eugene O'Neill principally consists of material that dates from the period of Agnes Boulton's and Eugene O'Neill's marriage. There is also some correspondence concerning Boulton's life after their divorce. The collection includes correspondence, writings of Agnes Boulton and of Eugene O'Neill, diaries of Agnes Boulton and of Eugene O'Neill, financial and legal documents, and photographs. The papers span the years 1910 to 1959, but the bulk of the material is from 1920 to 1927. The collection is organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Personal Papers, and is housed in seven boxes.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: General Correspondence, Family Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically. The first subseries, General Correspondence, contains mostly incoming letters to Boulton and O'Neill; folders that also contain letters from Boulton or O'Neill (penciled drafts, typed carbons, or typed originals) have been noted in the container list. Letters from people not listed individually may be found in "letter" general files.
The general correspondence is a mixture of professional and personal. There are letters requesting permission from O'Neill to perform his plays, and letters from the American Play Company (O'Neill's agent) regarding his plays, as well as letters from the O'Neills' governess, Fifine Clark; correspondence regarding Boulton's divorce from O'Neill (letters to Boulton from her lawyer, Arthur F. Driscoll, and from O'Neill's lawyer, Harry Weinberger); and letters from Frederick Parsell Hill, the architect who worked on Spithead, the O'Neills' house in Bermuda. Correspondence from the period following Boulton's divorce from O'Neill is in this series as well, including an exchange of letters with Max Wylie regarding Boulton's book, Part of a Long Story (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1958), in which she describes two years (1917-1919) of the time she spent with O'Neill. Their correspondence also concerns Wylie's book, Trouble in the Flesh, a novel based on O'Neill's life, which was also published by Doubleday, in 1959.
The second subseries, Family Correspondence, contains letters of the Boulton family (Boulton's sisters, Cecil Boulton Fisk and Margaret Boulton; and her brother-in-law, Edward Fisk) and of the O'Neill family (O'Neill's sons, Shane Rudraighe and Eugene, Jr.; his daughter, Oona; and his third wife, Carlotta Monterey O'Neill). The correspondence between Boulton and O'Neill consists mostly of telegrams (with mention of homesickness, missing each other, and travel arrangements). There is a letter from O'Neill's brother, James, Jr. to O'Neill regarding their father's health, and three letters from O'Neill's mother, Mary Ellen Quinlan O'Neill, to Boulton and O'Neill about Peaked Hill Bar and about Shane. The third subseries, Third Party Correspondence, contains a few exchanges, including a letter from the actress Mary Blair to the O'Neills' governess, Fifine Clark, about hiring Clark, and two letters between Shane Rudraighe O'Neill and his governess, Fifine Clark.
Series II, Writings, is organized into three subseries, Agnes Boulton, Eugene O'Neill, and Others. The Agnes Boulton subseries contains typescript carbon copies of notes and short personal writings by Boulton, mostly about her marriage to O'Neill. These copies were probably made either by Boulton or by Max Wylie from Boulton's penciled notes (which are not in this collection) while she was working on Part of a Long Story. The Eugene O'Neill subseries contains typescripts and carbons of ten early poems by O'Neill, which date from 1910 to 1915; some are undated. There is a typescript of the third act of The Guilty One, a play that was a collaboration between O'Neill and Boulton. In addition, there is a typescript carbon copy of O'Neill's introduction to White Buildings by Hart Crane, which was probably typed by Boulton or Wylie from the original typescript (now housed in the Berg Collection of the New York Public Library). There is also a fragment of a character study by O'Neill called "Ole Oleson's saga." The final subseries contains a typescript carbon fragment of Robert Frost's play, "A Way Out."
Series III, Personal Papers, is organized into three subseries, Diaries, Financial and Legal Materials, and Photographs. The first subseries, Diaries, contains two diaries by Boulton, as well as her loose diary notes. The first diary is from 1925 but also contains some entries for 1927; the second diary is from 1928. In both diaries, the entries are sporadic and mainly cover Boulton's activities and thoughts, with some notes on O'Neill. The loose diary notes date from 1919 to 1925 and are mostly her thoughts on her life and on O'Neill. This subseries also contains O'Neill's diary for 1925, which contains notes on his writing, as well as on his activities. O'Neill's practice seems to have been to copy a group of diaries over a five-year period into a single five-year work diary. These five-year work diaries are located in the Eugene O'Neill Papers (YCAL MSS 123). O'Neill's note in the front of the work diary for 1924-28 (see YCAL MSS 123, box 78, folder 1437) states that the diary for 1925 was reconstructed "from memory + few records, diary of that year having been stolen + sold by former wife." The 1925 diary to which he refers is the one located in this subseries.
The second subseries, Financial and Legal Materials, consists mostly of bills (for books, clothing, telegrams, and medical expenses). In addition, the files contain legal documents regarding O'Neill and Boulton's homes (Brook Farm, Ridgefield, Conn.; Peaked Hill Bar, Provincetown, Mass.; and Spithead, Bermuda Islands) and their divorce.
The third subseries, Photographs, includes several informal snapshots of O'Neill, as well as pictures of O'Neill's and Carlotta's dogs, Ben and Blemie; Shane and Oona's nanny, Fifine Clark ("Gaga"); Kathleen Millay; and a view of the drive at Château du Plessis, where O'Neill and Carlotta lived in France from 1929 to 1930.
Part of a long story; American literature -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century; Playwriting; Diaries -- United States -- 20th Century; Poetry; Boulton, Agnes, 1893-1968; Hill, Frederick Parsell, 1862-1957; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953 -- Homes and haunts -- Bermuda Islands; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953 -- Homes and haunts -- Connecticut -- Ridgefield; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953 -- Homes and haunts -- Massachusetts -- Provincetown; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953; Weinberger, Harry, 1888-; Wylie, Max, 1904-; American Play Company
- Correspondence, 1917-1959; Series I; 1.0' (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: General Correspondence, Family Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically. Letters from correspondents not listed individually may be found in "letter" general files. Unidentified correspondence is arranged at the end of the first subseries.
  - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE
    - "A" general, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Center of P.E.N., 1922, 1929, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Play Company, 1920-28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American-Scandinavian Foundation, 1919, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Authors Club (New York, N.Y.), 1922, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "B" general, 1921-27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Baker, Christina H., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      i.e., Mrs. George Pierce Baker.
    - Banks, Edgar James, 1924 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Barbour, Charlotte, [1926, 1927] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      With one TL from AB to Barbour, 1926 Aug 9.
    - Belasco, David, 1925 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Carbon from EO.
    - Bianco, Francesco, 1921-24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Blair, Mary, [1928?] Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Incomplete.
    - Blinn, Holbrook, 1922 Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Boni & Liveright, 1926 Sep 17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bonney, Louise, [1922 Sep?] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bonney, M. Thérèse, 1922 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Boyd, Ernest Augustus, 1921 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Boyd, Madeleine Elise Reynier, 1925 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Breuer, Bessie, [1926], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bunner, Alice L., 1921-22 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      i.e., Mrs. H. C. Bunner.
    - "C" general, 1919-58, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Cadenas, Frances, 1923 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Regarding James O'Neill, Jr.
    - Carlin, Terry, [1926] Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      With two bills and two letters from C. L. Burch & Son for supplies for Carlin, 1924-25.
    - Carter, Leslie, Mrs., 1922 Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Clark, Barrett Harper, 1919-21 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Clark, Fifine, 1922-29, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      i.e., "Gaga." With three ALS from AB.
    - Clark, Rufus L., 1926 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      With signed lease for Loon Lodge in Belgrade Lakes, Maine, 1926 Jun 30.
    - Clark University (Worcester, Mass.), 1922 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Columbia University, 1920, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      With printed announcement of 1922 Pulitzer Prizes.
    - Cowley, Malcolm, [1926?] (Box 1, Folder 30)
      ALS from AB.
    - Cowley, Peggy Baird, [1958?] Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Malcolm Cowley, box 1, folder 30
    - Crane, Hart, 1923-26 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "D" general, 1921-26 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Deeter, Jasper, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Demuth, Charles, 1919-26, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - De Polo, Harold, 1926-57, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Drama League of America, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Dreiser, Theodore, 1919 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Driscoll, Arthur F., 1928-29 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Dunsany, Edward John Moreton Drax Plunkett, Baron, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - "E" general, 1924-25 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Elizabethan Club (Yale University), 1921-22 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Ell, Christine, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Ervine, St. John G., 1920-22 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "F" general, 1922-24, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Fitzgerald, M. Eleanor, 1923-25 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      With one TL 1925 Jan 26, and one ALS, [1925?] Mar 28, from AB.
    - Francis, John A., 1918, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - "G" general, 1922-59, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Gaylord Farm Sanatorium, 1921-26 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Geddes, Norman Bel, 1922-24 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Gish, Lillian, 1927 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Glaspell, Susan, [1920], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Gold, Michael, [1925 Jun 23] (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Gray & Smith, 1929-30 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Gregory, Montgomery, 1923 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - "H" general, 1922-26, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Hale, Ruth, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Hamilton, G. V., 1926, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Hansford, Montiville M., 1925-26 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Hapgood, Hutchins, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Harvard Club of New York City, 1921-26 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Hiebert, Daniel H., 1925 Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Hill, Frederick Parsell, 1926-27 (Box 1, Folder 63)
      Includes three carbons from AB, and three carbons and one TL (draft), corrected, from EO.
    - Jones, Robert Edmond (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - "K" general, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Kallen, Horace Meyer, 1926 Jan 26 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Karsner, David, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Keane, Doris, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Kenton, Edna, 1924 Feb 3 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Komroff, Manuel, [1928] (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - "L" general, 1921-26, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 71)
      Includes enclosed photograph of drawing, "Provincetown Theater Group and Friends" by William L'Engle.
    - Langner, Lawrence, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Light, James, 1920, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, [1926] Aug 13 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Lyman, David Russell
      See: Gaylord Farm Sanatorium, box 1, folder 49
    - "M" general, 1921-24 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - McCardell, Roy L., 1920 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Macgowan, Kenneth, 1925-26 (Box 2, Folder 77)
      With one ALS from Edna Macgowan, undated, and one TL (incomplete) from EO.
    - Mack, Willard, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Madden, Richard J.
      See: American Play Company, box 1, folder 3
      See: The New-York American, box 2, folder 88
    - Maloney, William Joseph Marie Alois, 1923-25 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Marbury, Elisabeth, 1925-29 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Markham, Kyra, 1959 Apr 17 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Metropolitan (New York, N.Y.), 1918 Aug 13 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Middleton, George, 1920-23 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Millay, Cora B., 1920 Dec 22 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Moise, Nina, [1920 Jan 16] (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - "N" general, 1922, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, 1920 Nov 10 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - The New-York American, [1922], 1928 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Includes drafts to Richard J. Madden Play Company, Inc. and to Elizabeth Shepley Sergeant.
    - New York Drama League, Inc., 1920-22 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - "O" general, 1923, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - "P" general, 1918-26 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Phelps, William Lyon, 1921-22 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Players (Club), 1958 Mar 24 (Box 2, Folder 93)
      With one carbon from AB, 1958 Mar 12.
    - Pond, James B., 1922 Mar 23 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Princeton University, 1921 Jun 23 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - "Q" general, 1922, [1925] (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Quinn, Arthur Hobson, 1921-22 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - "R", general (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Rauh, Ida, 1920 Feb 4 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Richards, William A., 1925 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      With one carbon from AB, 1925 Aug 22.
    - Richman, Arthur, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Robeson, Paul, Jr., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - "S" general, 1920-21 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Schwimmer, Rosika, 1922 Sep 27 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Sergeant, Elizabeth Shepley, 1926-28, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 105)
      See also: The New-York American, box 2, folder 88
    - Seven Arts (New York, N.Y.), 1917 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Sing Sing Correctional Facility, 1921 Jan 15 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Southern New England Telephone Company, 1921 Sep 19 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Speiser, Maurice J., 1922 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Steele, Wilbur Daniel, 1920 Nov 17 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - "T" general, 1922-26 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Throckmorton, Cleon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - University of Colorado, Boulder, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - University of Montana (Missoula), 1923 Jul 9 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - "V" general, 1922 Jul 27 (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Vanity Fair (New York, N.Y.), 1922 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Visser, Peter J., 1922 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - "W" general, 1921, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Walker, Charles Rumford, 1922 Jun 16 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Washington University (Saint Louis, Mo.), 1923 Aug 2 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Weinberger, Harry, 1926-39 (Box 2, Folder 121-122)
    - Wilson, Edmund, 1927 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - World (New York, N.Y.), 1922 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Wylie, Lambie, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 125)
      With one TL (carbon) from AB, 1958 Mar 9.
    - Wylie, Max, 1956-57, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 126)
      With one TL (carbon) from AB, 1957 Nov 25.
    - ----, Tony, 1925 Sep 19 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
    Boulton, Agnes
    - To Cecil Boulton Fisk, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 128)
    - To Eugene O'Neill, 1920-29, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 129)
    - To Shane Rudraighe O'Neill, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 130)
    - Boulton, Margaret to Agnes Boulton, 1921 Nov 2 (Box 3, Folder 131)
    - [Fisk, Cecil Boulton?] to Eugene O'Neill, [1926 Nov] (Box 3, Folder 132)
    - Fisk, Edward William to Agnes Boulton, [1922, 1923] (Box 3, Folder 133)
    - O'Neill, Carlotta Monterey
      - To Agnes Boulton, [1926 Dec?] (Box 3, Folder 134)
      - To Oona Chaplin, 1933-37 (Box 3, Folder 135)
      - To Shane Rudraighe O'Neill, 1931-41, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 136)
    - O'Neill, Eugene
      - To Agnes Boulton, 1918-28 (Box 3, Folder 137)
      - To Shane Rudraighe O'Neill, 1939, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 138)
    - O'Neill, Eugene, Jr. to Agnes Boulton, [1925] (Box 3, Folder 139)
    - O'Neill, James, Jr. to Eugene O'Neill, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 140)
    - O'Neill, Mary Ellen Quinlan to Agnes Boulton and Eugene O'Neill, 1919-20 (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Besnard, Lucien to Mr. Filene, 1922 Feb 22 (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - Blair, Mary to Fifine Clark, [1927?] (Box 3, Folder 143)
      To Gaga.
    - Clark, Fifine to Shane Rudraighe O'Neill, [1926, 1927?] (Box 3, Folder 144)
    - Francis, John A. to Margery Stevens, 1926 Feb 10 (Box 3, Folder 145)
    - O'Neill, Shane Rudraighe to Fifine Clark, [1928] (Box 3, Folder 146)
      In hand of [Custis Lee Bradley?].
    - Selwyn, Edgar to George Jean Nathan, 1921 Mar 10 (Box 3, Folder 147)
- Writings, 1910-1915; Series II; 0.20' (1 box)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into three subseries: Agnes Boulton, Eugene O'Neill, and Others.
  - AGNES BOULTON
    - "Agnes: -- Thoughts on Her Marriage," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 148)
      With manuscript comments in an unidentified hand.
    - "Eugene's Drinking," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 149)
    - "Fragment from Agnes' Manuscript, Flung into Fire by Eugene," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 150)
      Also includes "Letter to Agnes from Her Mother, Litchfield, R.D. #1, Feb. 23, 1922" and "Letter from Agnes' Mother (After Agnes' Divorce), New Preston, Sept. 27th."
    - "Max Wylie Interview with Martha Dean[e] on WOR, May First 1959," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 151)
    - "Outline for 'The Captain's Walk' -- Agnes (Pencil)," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 152)
    - "Part of a Long Story," poem, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - EUGENE O'NEILL
    - Poems
      - "Ballade of the Two of Us," typescript carbon, 1910 Jan 11 (Box 4, Folder 154)
      - "Beyond the Great Divide," typescript carbon (Box 4, Folder 155)
      - "Full Many a Cup of This Forbidden Wine," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 156)
      - [The golden oranges in the patio...], typescript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 157)
      - "Just a Little Love, a Little Kiss," typescript carbon, 1915 Jan 9 (Box 4, Folder 158)
      - "Just Me N' You (From a Child to a Child)," typescript carbon, 1910 Jan 15 (Box 4, Folder 159)
      - "Lament for Beatrice," typescript carbon, 1915 Jan 15 (Box 4, Folder 160)
      - "Lament of a Subwayite (W. A. to J. Milton)," typescript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 161)
      - "Rondeau: To Her Nose," typescript carbon, 1915 Jan 13 (Box 4, Folder 162)
      - "Villanelle to His Ladye," typescript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 163)
    - Other Writings
      - [The Guilty One]. Act III, play, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 164)
        Collaboration with AB. Corrections by EO and by AB.
      - "Introduction" [to White Buildings by Hart Crane], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 165)
        Probably typed by AB or Max Wylie in 1950s.
      - [Ole Oleson's saga], character study, typescript carbon (fragment), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - OTHERS
    - Frost, Robert. "A Way Out," play, typescript carbon (fragment), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 167)
- Personal Papers, 1912-1949; Series III; 0.60' (2 boxes)
  Series II, Personal Papers, is organized into three subseries: Diaries, Financial and Legal Materials, and Photographs.
  - DIARIES
    - Agnes Boulton
      - Diary notes, 1919-25 (Box 5, Folder 168)
      - Diary, 1925, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 169)
      - Diary, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 170)
    - Eugene O'Neill
      - Diary, holograph, in volume, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 171)
        In "Charles Letts's Popular Scribbling Diary."
  - FINANCIAL AND LEGAL MATERIALS
    - Books. Bills for, 1923-26, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 172)
    - Brook Farm (Ridgefield, Conn.). Bills and letters regarding, 1923-27, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - Checks, cancelled, 1924-25 (Box 6, Folder 174)
      One from EO to Hotel Lafayette; two from AB to Fifine Clark.
    - Clothing. Bills for, 1922-26 (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - Divorce. Legal documents regarding, 1928-47 (Box 6, Folder 176)
    - Miscellaneous bills, 1923-27 (Box 6, Folder 177)